I'll just run you through. I caught this low. I caught many of these highs as scalps and countertrend trades. I caught today this morning this low, this high, this low. I missed that because I was sleeping. And just now we just tag this level. But I expect it, because now what I'd expect this to continue running for the rest of the day. But it's scope for it to draw back into range. But let me just give you an idea, yeah? So that's about 50 pips. I think catch this low.
but that's 50 pips.
This was about 34 pips.
When you say you were sleeping,
did you not have like a limit on,
but you didn't get tagged?
No, if I had a limit, this would have got tagged.
Oh, would it?
The reason I don't like putting limits in is like,
imagine the likelihood of the initial response is higher.
Yeah, yeah?
And I can manage that response.
It puts me in a position where I can view incoming price action
to determine if it's likely to continue up,
or if it's going to fail.
Oh, okay.
so yeah you need to be actively on the charts don't you to
I want to be actively at the charts
now depending on the level as well
this isn't like the best of levels
if you contextualize where that falls in
it looks like a breakout accumulation
on the fractal apex I agree
on this fractal apex but
broadly speaking within the broader scope
that's the shelf
that was the shelf anyway
this is the last semblance tree that pushed it to new highs
yeah so
that's a shelf on the H1 of the H1
price swing but also because price is fractal that is a fractal apex as well okay you get it yeah yeah um
it's not the b a specifically this is the b a down here this is more the shelf retest okay right because
the b a is the one that pushes through the shelf mm-hmm not the one that uh retests it so if i draw
an apex here price is selling the cell inventory moving down and then we come into last
sell inventory fails to push to new lows, indicative that the sell inventory is now weaker or
the sticker by liquidity here. It typically takes multiple attempts and it fails and then price pushes
through. Okay. The area, the inventory, the liquidity base that pushed through the shelf
is the breakout accumulation. That's the definition of it. Okay. If price returns back down and
retest the BA, we call that the shelf retest. Okay.
It won't always have a B.A. level there, but it's still classed at the shelf retest.
And then this we would call the retest of the shelf retest or the child shelf retest, right?
Because it's the second one. It's the child of the first one.
Now, not all price swings and apexes will develop that way.
They could quite easily come all the way back down to the lows, not break the low, but come all the way back down to the low and then continue.
Now this turns into the B.A.
Okay. Yeah. All right. So BA is at quite a significant level, but it's not always going to be responsive. Here we just looked at an example where the BA failed. Price went straight through it down to the bottom side. All right. But all of these levels, the bottom are basically the pickup. That's the first pickup of by liquidity. Yeah. The pickup, the fractal apex retest, this is a fractal apex retest. This is a fractal apex retest there. And then this was the original BA failed to hold.
and price came down.
All of these three levels that I've just described
fall inside of the core area of liquidity
of any single price run, which is the origin.
Yeah.
So what I'm saying here, there'll be a pickup,
on the low time frame at least,
there'll be some form of fractal apex retest,
and there's also going to be some BA
within every single apex that exists.
So every single apex is classed as core liquidity
relative to the timeframe of the price run.
Within core areas of liquidity,
you have the pickup, the retest,
and then the BA.
So there's three levels there inside of them,
which are quite significant.
They fall inside of a thick area of liquidity.
But the reason we define,
you know,
we refine them into three pockets
and not just this one big pocket
is so that we get basically tied to risk.
You know,
taking a trade with a three-pip stop.
So, you know, imagine you're going to risk
five pound on a trade, yeah?
On one trade,
you have a stop loss of 10 pips.
You risk five pound across,
10 pips. On the other trade, you risk five pound
across two pips.
Which one, you know, here
every time price moves up, you make
five pound. Every time price moves up
two pips, you move five pound, five pound, five pound, five pound.
To make five pound here has to move up ten pips.
Right? So to make the same amount of money
relative to the size of your stop loss and obviously your position
sizing, the tight to your stop is the bigger your reward.
So if you ever see my levels like this, I caught this
So the three pip stop.
It was about three point something pips,
but the stop goes directly past the level.
Do you get it?
So enter here, stop directly past the level,
have it pre-planned.
And imagine, just for example,
I don't risk five pound,
but imagine it was five pound,
risked across three pips,
three pips up, five pound, six,
right, you get it.
So this is the reason we go into this process of refining level.
So we can basically tighten up our risk
and there is an observable.
So you can validate,
this you've probably seen it by this point
price tends to respond off the boxes I draw
not because I'm special it's just because we can
observe and identify
refined pockets of liquidity with a high level
of accuracy yeah it's actually
I guess like a process and doing it
where price is much more likely to respond
so basically identifying areas where there's
leftover liquidity or with liquidity will turn up
you get it yeah it came down to that level
as you wanted as well
came down very thin
yeah all of these
dripping price runs they're all coming in thin
even early morning today came in thin
this came in thin
this move actually broke midflow here
yeah price was selling selling
came all the way back up broke the last
infantry which is obviously a sign of weakness
yeah that was the parabolic phase
and then shot it responded
off this fractal apex here
you know this is also a fractal core
of this price swing
it basically got the top of it
then went to the bottom
look how like pinpoint it is it goes to the bottom
yeah
absorbs that liquidity
so whatever liquidity here is now
X this has been filled
it's been fulfilled or picked up
and then price pushes through to the next level
where there's more significant equity
yeah which is the core now
which is still inside the core yeah so out of
these two levels here this is the
BA and this is a less
significant level even though it
will respond and price this is where you had the bigger move off right even here today we have a
well yesterday we had a a a fractal price swing a b and you know price sold off yeah now if you look at
the shelf of this move up we have a shelf retest and the b a then that price retest before it price
shifts out to bullish midflow base run base holds
run base holes run deep test but base holes run this last base holds and then here's your first
break of midflow yeah it runs out it's still within that sideways phase no clear parabolic phase
but still price dries off yeah and this is now the last inventory that pushed it to new highs
price draws back down comes up for a so in this instance we're here price was inside of the shelf
when it retested the apex this broke the shelf and then came back and retested the apex
did it come just just the same or did it just go past i can't tell let me show you it it looked like
it just came right up to the top didn't it didn't go past it but i'll prove it to you this is a higher
low label yeah it's drawn on by the yeah she's a high and the low yeah this is still inside
that's still inside the height but this is the one that probably shifted out from it to bearish midflow
So that's the BA, this whole fractal.
Yeah.
Right.
And today this morning, we came to BA.
So BA is quite responsive.
But the point I'm raising here is, yeah, in this example, price retests, builds up and pushes
through the shot this way.
The sell liquidity in the shelf is picked up and somewhere it follows down, fails to push
to the new lows, buyers are quite, buyers are absorbing sellers.
Price comes up again to sell the query, fails to push, fails to push.
it's absorbing whatever sell liquidity is there.
We know that.
Or at least the market order buyers are eating
those that sell liquidity there.
But this anatomically, visually,
is almost,
you know, not almost, but it's very different visually
to what this looks like.
If I was to flip this around,
it would look more like this.
Here's the shelf.
Price pushes through the shelf,
comes all the way back down for a retest
and then breaks through.
Visually they look very, very different.
But the characteristics,
are exactly the same
in terms of what matters for Apex
the low held
that's it
in every one of these instances
in every successful Apex
the original pick-up will hold
here price comes
holds inside the shelf
draws back down for Apex
retest and then just shoots out
that is this
let me just show you
oh shit no it broke the shelf
right so here we poke through the shelf
comes back down
retest this kind of Apex
area and then
pushes through. And if I was to
zoom into this itself
we're going to see the same
characteristics of apex.
Why do you think the characteristics of apex
exist or occur?
There's a very simple answer to it.
Why do I think they occur?
There's a principle which kind of explains it.
Price moving to the less liquid side.
Okay, so price does do that.
Elaborate.
I don't, I want to, because you could be right with that answer if you, if you're
in the right way. Um, so obviously, because the, the shelf is the last inventory of, so in this
case, it's, uh, uh, it's, there's the sellers inside that shelf. Yeah.
And as long as price breaks through that shelf, then it's showing that the buyer, uh, the
sellers are weaker and the buyer is much stronger. I, I get what you're trying to say. Uh,
I agree.
So the answer to my question is basically price reflects state illiquity, yeah?
Yeah.
Whatever price does, it reflects the state of liquidity.
The apex is showing us now that the inventory, which has previously in the bear
enrichment flow, every single time price is fed off it, it's been able to push to new lows.
Every single time price comes on feeds off the sell inventory, pushes to new lows.
Feeds off the sell inventory, pushes to new lows.
And that's where you get the bearishment flow characteristics.
and then let's just say price breaks
forms of shelf now the sell inventory is weaker
and hence why price shows it
so the weakness of the shelf isn't necessarily
confirmed once price is pushed through
is actually confirmed in how price responds off it
you get it yeah it didn't get
there was no new lows from there was there
yeah basically yeah yeah so
not only was the no new lows in this specific instance
price actually pushed through the
shelf, which is a further
sign of weakness.
It's more favourable if I'm going
long. If I have a position long,
I would prefer if my first
run went through the shelf, compared
to held inside the shelf.
Very subtle differences,
but this increases the probability
of the trade working.
Or what you'll basically see is this
occur in that great higher
probability yourselves.
So, you know, the point of this question here
is that there's variations in what price can do.
in what apexes can look like
in what mid-flow can look like
in what shelf retest can look like
but all of them have the same characteristics
yeah
visually they can look different
they have the same characteristics
for example
someone can have big eyes
small eyes but the both are fucking two eyes
that's the characteristic
but anatomically and visually
one eye can be bent
or whatever right
the same kind of thing applies
for these variations
in each individual
price swing stage that's what they called
one price swing stage is the midflow
the strength phase
now by strength we're not talking about
how fast price is moving
we're talking about the fact that there's one
side of liquidity and weakness
on the other side
yeah yeah
and then in the sideways
the break of midflow and the pop
we're draining the inventory of that move
we know with the with the price run
inventory is moving along with it holding it down
trying to get filled
and then within the apex
we're seeing confirmation basis
basically. We see the visualization of the shift in the order flow. Now, we have to separate the
price swing stage from basically phrases we use to describe states and conditions. So in other words,
if I was identifying low liquid states where volume drops off, it is there, it does there,
it is there, it does there, it does it all the time. If I identified stages where volume shock
comes in and price becomes inefficient
it creates inefficiency
as market responds
the dynamics of markets kicks in
we're seeing it here
here even on the move down
even on the move up we're seeing exhaustion
etc these are price conditions
that will exist regardless of the price swing
stage yeah because they need to exist before
don't they? Yeah
they're not describing
anything to do with characteristics of a price
swing you get it they're describing
the dynamics of
price itself.
Low volume state is literally volume dropping off and not driving into sell limit orders
or bi limit orders.
There's stability in the market to limit order ratio.
That's what low volume state is describing.
The effect of low volume state or low liquidity state is one side of that will typically
weaken, right?
So there's 10 million sell limits, there's 10 million buy limits.
Market orders will continue to come in and absorb one side until let's just say there's
3 million left here.
If now a buy volume shot comes in, bear in mind, in a low liquidity state, price can go any
direction.
Yeah.
Right?
You could, in theory, have a volume shot on the sell side and cause the bids to withdraw,
cause the dealers to withdraw their bid and the market to chase their, the buy liquidity.
Or you can have the same thing with a buy volume shot, market order buy, and cause the sell
liquidity to disappear.
You get it.
Yeah.
Now, depending on the location of the low liquidity state, in this instance, you know, it's
instance, we just hit a nice pocket of wide liquidity, it's very likely you have thicker
bids, which won't go away. And depending on the, you know, considering the move down,
which is inefficient on the higher time frame, it's more likely that we have a weakness on
the sell limits. Yeah. But I think you understand my point. The, the states that we
describe, the liquidity states that we're describing here, or at least the price conditions
and the dynamics we're describing, exists regardless of where prices, what, you know, what
time of the day is it will always happen volume will always dry off variable volume flow you will
always get these periods which are reflections of just natural market you know just natural market
dynamics volume will not come in the same size all the time right and inefficiencies will exist
as a result of you could call basically we put it down to the collection of dynamics that exist
within microstructure yeah right
When I'm talking about a price swing stage then, this is the apex of this fractal price swing.
This is the apex, again, of these fractal price swings.
And then this is broadly the bigger apex of the higher time frame.
Relative to those small ones, this is the broader apex of the higher time frame.
You follow me.
All of these exist simultaneously and aren't describing the same thing as me saying,
this is low-volume state, this is low-volume state, this is low-volume state.
Obviously, we're seeing a directional volume here trying to fine-sell liquidity, and low-volume state, shot.
Low-volume state, surge.
We also see a low-volume state surge-out, price becomes super inefficient, and it always drives back in, draws back in.
Shoots out a low-volume state draws back in.
So that will happen regardless of the location or the point.
price week. It can happen during midflow. It can happen during apex, etc. You follow me?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So it's important to differentiate between them. All right, back to what we was
discussing. There's variations in the specific price swing stages. This is much more of a strong
midflow compared to this one, which broke quite early. This pushed in your eyes. It broke,
continued, broke again. Of this price went at least, you had a run, run, run, run, run.
side of it. It wasn't a clear side of its pop, but
it is the shelf, pushed the new highs,
broke shelf here,
and it didn't fill it back down.
Yeah.
Right? So we have a
low that's weak, another
low that's weak. Both of these
broke midflow, and we
continue, we have a bit of a pop, and then
let's see, you get your strong
sell-off. Think about it this way.
All these areas have been, prices
come back, and already grabbed them.
Come back, grabbed them. Come back, grab them.
come back, grab them.
It's drained the liquidity on the way up
with multiple breaks.
The liquidity itself,
the buy liquidity that was pushing along with price,
wasn't that strong.
Why?
It's not true question.
The characteristics of a strong run.
Oh, yeah, because it's already invalidated
the bases, the midflow isn't strong.
It's broke midflow, yeah.
So what you'll typically see
is in strong driven moves.
The last base will always hold.
It holds because of the way
the strength you know the liquidity so there's so much liquidity to that wants to get fulfilled
this 50 billion that wants to get filled that wants to get filled so wherever price goes there's
always liquidity with it close to it as that large order tries to get filtered into the market
or as participants filter their large orders into the market then when you have a move like
this which isn't a strong it isn't liquidity close the price all the time yeah price has to reach
all the way down here to find buyers
And then in this price,
when it has to reach down here,
pass the last inventory to find buyers.
This is a less,
in terms of the visual characteristics,
this mid-flow isn't as strong as this one.
And over time,
through validation and, you know,
basically doing your job,
you'll come to find that whenever there's a strong move,
it almost always looks like that.
Yeah.
Whenever you get the biggest moves
with the most volume behind them,
they always look like this.
They drive, there's liquidity.
So regardless of the way price goes,
price comes down here,
liquidity turns up there.
Yeah, it's more of an aggressive midflow, isn't it?
That one.
Yeah, when there's more volume to get filled.
Here, it's more passive.
It drains because it keeps coming back to pick you up,
keeps coming back to pick you up,
keeps coming back to pick liquidity off.
It drains it on the way up.
I mean, no price goes to a less liquid side.
So if there's like, broadly speaking,
by liquidity here has been drained,
this move makes sense
if there's a lack of liability there
any selling is likely to cause price to accelerate
volatility is a function of available liquidity
I know we responded off this low
which I call weak we did respond
but basically the point I would raise here is
you will never have a consistent edge
in risk taking a trade like this
off a level like that
so imagine price ran up and then it broke midflow yeah right dried off comes back down the probability
of it responding here consistently is not it's not there basically it might be 50 50 it might be 60 40
but over time you will not in my opinion at least it's very hard to find the edge in getting
consistent responses of this level it could quite easily poke past it basically to the next level and draw
back in you get it yeah so in this one example it seems to have responded but what you need is a
large sample set of experiences and you'll come to find that it often will not respond so even here yeah
we broke midflow and we responded it's exactly the same thing that's happened here price is running
price breaks midflow continues puts the high in calms down and responds off that level yeah so are you calling
it's weak because the midflow
is already broke before that
it's basically
two things it's a residual level
in the middle of this price run
yeah oh yeah yeah yeah so we know it's week
and then also
it's washed which I haven't introduced it to this concept
yeah basically there was liquidity here
but we drained the liquidity
so it's washed
there's week times two basically
now that doesn't mean there's
absolutely no liquidity there
there was some liquidity there
and because of this movie
and so stretched the downside
the further price runs the weaker it gets
it ended up leaving a vacuum
a vacuum of sell liquidity
so once
the offers dried of the selling dried off and price
drew back into range on buying
there wasn't enough sell liquidity to keep
powering it down it had to draw back in for
a bigger shelf retest
a proper swing retest of shelf
the point I'm making
is we now have two examples
of a level like that working
which is washed and residual
but it's not enough evidence or data
for you to consistently take that trade
and make money off it.
Yeah, you'd much rather wait
for the 90, 10, than a 60, 40.
If, you know, like, if over time
you've observed this to have edge,
then you will, you know,
you will take that step in trying to exploit it
because you as Zane,
have seen it over and over and over again,
you've got your sample set,
so you don't need me to tell you,
you get it, so you have to validate
and build these experiences,
but what I'm telling you is
you will have these types of levels
which are not great
which I don't have edge in them
there's no positive expectancy there
but will still respond
and look that ended up causing response
for 170
well it started at
1130 you went to half 12
yeah sorry it was a half an hour
response so for a whole half an hour
you had four all to do
it could quite easily have extended
through to the better levels
and you know
when you're
alive and you're trading and you're looking for trades if the inexperienced mind is at the charts
they'll quite easily think they've missed out on a trade here but in reality there's no great
edge in taking that trade we're just having an instance where the outcome of price responding there
you know it's distributing randomly so is you know this could happen for the next 10 times
yeah it doesn't mean shit it's over a very large sample where you get a true you know a true
reflection of probabilities over a very large sample.
It's called a lot of large numbers, yeah?
So in other words, you know, if you want to see, if you flip a coin 50-50 heads, tails,
you will only get 50 outcomes heads, oh, sorry, 50% of the outcomes heads and 50% of the
outcomes tails over a very, very big number of flips.
We're talking two, three, four hundred thousand flips.
And not every single time as well.
you could have a time where you flip the coin, you know, the coin 200 times and you still have one side more than the other.
The closer you get to infinity, the more accurately, the probabilities will be reflected.
So when you have this level, which is not so great, residual and washed, you could quite easily get price responding there three, four, five times in a row.
And that could happen over the next week, but still there's no great edge in trading there.
Now, maybe what you can do is identify the environment, the higher time frame state of liquidity, where these levels are worthwhile taking.
So, for example, what I'll do, I'll delete this shit.
I hope you follow me, but you know, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So I'll draw these two as green boxes so we can see that.
Basically, the point I'm making is we didn't, we have residual and wash levels, yeah?
You're not for great.
I was going to say, so, yeah, we're talking about the character.
268 packs out the
variations
you need to express the variations
so yeah
that was made in the discussion
so what we're basically doing
is we're looking at price
and you know what price does
so in all of these instances
when price is responding
you can actually see it's super thin
yeah yeah yeah
so the kind of characteristics
I'm looking for when I'm taking entries
but anyway
so did you manage to
have a look at
examples in your chart of price
like we discussed what did you go through the you know the yeah the the last thing you
told me to do was to just go and check through you know how you annotate you said that
i'll need i'll need it in the next few lessons or so yeah yeah yeah yeah i just wanted to
make sure that you had a bit of chance you know a chance to look over what prices have been
doing yeah yeah um because these price swings are so consistent and they're everywhere
turning up you know here we have one run there you have a run down you have a fractal run up
etc etc in every single one of them
price is following a sequence of stages
so you know we'll have a midflow
then the midflow shows weakness
price then goes into a bit of a low volume state stability
all of these are low volume states yeah
and then you have high volume low volume high volume
and then you have a surge typically
that suppose the end it will typically reach for an area
of significant liquidity and then goes into the apex stage
now the idea here is
the cell inventory should be weaker
than the buye inventory down there
buy liquidity down there
so we want to see price show that in the response
so how we're response off the shelf
hopefully it shows us
ideally price can break through the shell
confirming the weakness in the shell
but you have to remember
probability is a dynamic
just because this has broke the shell
doesn't mean the slow will hold
yeah yeah of course
future probabilities can change
instantaneously
but as of right now
this is good information
there's an ideal information
if we're looking for a reversal
is showing our signs of weakness
if I'm going long
I want sell weakness
at this stage
the apex needs to hold
sorry the original pickup
the OPE
it picked up the bi-liquity
and we wanted to hold
right
we're going to talk about
in next session probably
how the probabilities
significantly change
if price actually
actually pokes past that low.
Okay.
All right, so I'll give you an example.
Yeah, so basically the low needs to hold.
The original pickup.
So what I mean,
but the original pickup is only validated.
Once prices grab the level and it's gone to the shelf,
then that pick up.
Okay.
If prices have just gone into the level and it hasn't done anything,
it's not clustered as a pickup.
Oh, okay, okay, okay.
All right?
So I'll give you an example.
Just give me one second, bro.
Yeah, yeah.
You're all working.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
cool so yeah that one's a good one right there yeah so here's the pickup draws into the shelf
that's an area of cell inventory if the bids are strong the idea is the inventory of sell liquidity
should not be able to absorb the bids in that pickup yeah right it draws down invalidates
in this instance it actually runs back in you see yeah still the likelihood of this low
holding is is even that small subtle that that small subtle new
once shifts the probabilities of it
holding significantly and price continues
compare that to this
apex, goes into the shelf,
draws back down, holds
and think about it, you're following
it sequentially.
When we're looking for an apex, we don't know if it's
going to hold or not, so we're looking for characteristics
of apexes that are
more favourable than others.
Here it holds, shifts into midflow.
So the sequence as it goes
is midflow, break a midflow
sideways pop that's the parabolic phase then we want the shelf to ideally break the retest the fractal
apex retest build up and then once you get through the shelf it won't go into midflow straight away
right this run itself is a fractal priced run it'll have its own individual features
very likely will dry off and we want a shelf retest okay i want the shelf retest but again there's
variations in apexes it could quite easily draw
lacking for another apex re-test.
But in other case, the characteristics of the apex remain the same.
The low holds, the shelf breaks, from here, we're expecting a shift in the stay of liquidity.
So in the move down, the inventory is moving down with the run.
You will typically get some form of shift where, as you push through the shelf, the sell liquidity withdraws.
And prices typically expand.
So we're breaking that structure down.
into individual pieces
characterising the individual features
of those stages
so we can better identify them
when we're trying to contextualize price.
So the framework
from which we view price
is characteristics of price swing.
We use it to track probabilities,
select trades, manage trades,
time trades alongside
accurately being able to give price
a context at any given time.
Think about it.
What does midflow mean?
If you see price in midflow, what is it showing you?
Showing you strengthen one direction.
If you wanted to look for a reversal, then, what characteristics would you want?
So you'd want to see midflow break, so a base break, and then typically maybe a stronger level it's reacting off.
so no like every single price one you see will break midflow yeah and then it will have a sideways
pop or at least the most favorable price swings it will have the sideways spot so in terms of
timing or reversal if prices in midflow you know there's no reversal there's no current price swing
stage shows you that the strength on one side there's no there's no merit in it to look for a reversal
until you get that break in midflow until you get that parabolic phase which drains the inventory
of that move so again tying it back to why we're looking at these cover
logistics, CPS is allowing us to break price down into individual stages in order for us to
select trades, time trades, trade the current environment appropriately.
The type of trades are going to get in mid-flow, entirely different to the sub-trades you'll get
the apex.
You get it.
So each part that we're looking at, the price is a component or a feature of price behavior
which falls in inside the price swing.
They're independent of the swing, each feature is.
We isolate those features to determine.
at this point anyway you're trying to isolate the individual stages to determine what type of
trading is going to allow us to carry out okay right so the purpose is detailing the features and
stages to clearly be able to distinguish between variations in price state we can connect that state
with the characteristics in price behaviors all of this allows you like it basically results in
the deeper understanding of price behavior how it's related to volatility um it is important to know that the
sequence is used to set expectations for favourable development.
It's not guaranteed.
We're just hoping that each individual stage will result in,
yeah, we'll be using it to basically manage an identified context.
Anyway, so the CPS, the price swing is the structure on which price moves.
It doesn't happen.
It is what price is the way price moves.
price swings are everywhere as a result of the market dynamics we've discussed so what we're doing
is we're looking at that structure in price and breaking it down to pieces okay what do you think
the benefit of that is what you can see kind of like what what characteristics you're looking
for in price would you say what kind of like environment you're in basically yeah yeah
because midflow will have it's completely different to trading in there and the end
the apex, the price is in a low volume state.
Yeah. Right.
Within a single price swing, you have three different stages.
The apex, the midflow, and then the sideways pop.
And then that reverses on the way down.
The apex, the midflow, the sideways pop.
Each of those follow each other, yeah?
So it's a sequence of events that takes place.
What we're doing is we're breaking it down into that sequence.
Yeah.
So we can, in the future, better contextualize price.
So right now, what should price do in this particular?
the price swing. So it's flip the shelf,
the residual levels
most likely not going to hold
so come back down to the core?
It should go into the barishment flow.
If we're looking at this price swing in isolation,
obviously you have other context. You do have higher
time frame. This could quite easily
be the higher time frame shelf
and this could quite easily
the higher time frame price swing doesn't have to be over.
So we might see it could easily continue
to the upside. And then
that's introducing a new principle that the higher
time frame governs the lower
time frame basically. High time frame takes
precedence. If the higher time frame
is abolish midflow
is this is H1 chart
and then this price swing alone
breaks shelf, that shelf break means nothing.
That's only the break of that fractal swing
whereas the higher time frame still has a huge
inventory of bi liquidity here. It could
quite easily continue.
So that's a new principle that the higher time frame
takes precedence or it governs price
movement, it governs the lower time frame.
So it's important at least to conceptualize why we're using price swings, yeah,
or why we're breaking down to the stages.
It allows us to accurately contextualize the environment, like you said.
Yeah.
Price swings are the structure in which price moves.
So it makes sense to, you know, use that, it makes sense to break that sequence down
so we can contextualize in live time, at least, what price is doing.
Mid-flow, again, like I said, we'll have different types of, it'll have variations.
This is quite efficient.
You see price extend out, draw back in.
Extend out, draw back in.
Yeah, extend it out.
It's now filled that extension.
Even here, extension, fill.
Extension, fill.
Small extension, fill.
All these characteristics are repeating over and over and over again.
If I was trading this bullish mid-flow, I know the extension past this high is likely to fill,
but I also know
that the cell liquidity here
is not strong enough
to continue power
and price down
so because
you know
we contextualize this
as a shelf flip
we expect bullish
made flow
but simultaneously
we can also anticipate
that these extensions
will get filled
so price extends out
there's a pot
it becomes super super
inefficient there
picks up a fractal core
cell liquidity on the left
now
we can expect
the extension to get filled
you get it
but because
the current environment is bullish mid-flow,
the likelihood of price breaking past the slice inventory
is very low.
So because I successfully identify the environment,
it influences how long I expect my trade,
how long I expect to hold my trade.
I don't look for a massive reversal
because I know the sell liquidity is weak,
but I'm also still able to exploit the price behavior,
which is highly likely,
which is extensions will get filled.
This run out is not seeing all the
The bulk of the liquidity, the inventory of this move is remaining down here.
So price fills it, picks up the bulk, builds up, and then it runs out again.
It runs, becomes super, super inefficient there, draws back down.
This isn't a great high, but it repeats over and over and over again.
So that's just one example of how contextualizing the environment can help, can I help influence or help us manage the trade, manage the trade.
select the trade, even time the trade,
here we're waiting for this fractal price swing here
to show weakness.
If I look inside of that,
so if I look inside of that,
midflow, base holds, base holds,
base holds, base holds, base holds,
price runs, and it becomes super, super, super, super thin up there.
Right?
It becomes the most inefficient has been at the highs.
Hopefully, we've already selected our levels on the left.
If we look at the level this hit as well,
apex.
it actually hit a fractal apex of that swing there.
Do you get it?
So on one part, we're identifying our levels of liquidity
where price might respond.
That's one part.
That's half the equation.
But then we're also looking at price movement into our levels.
Yeah, how it's coming.
Which increases the likelihood of the price response there.
In either case, you know, level plus price delivery
is just for increasing the likelihood of response
when we take the entry.
How long I expect my response.
how big I expect my response to be,
how long I expect my,
no,
how long I expect to trade,
to hold my trade,
the types of responses we can expect,
they are nothing to do with this.
This is just for timing and increasing the likelihood of the trade.
A response.
How would I know then,
whether I want to hold my trade,
whether I want to hold it past this area,
et cetera, et cetera.
Well, like you said,
higher time frame,
what it's showing,
like you said,
it could be just be...
The context.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, a higher time frame, shall flip.
Exactly the context.
So what stage of the price swing over yen?
Here we're in bullish midflow.
What are the characteristic to bullish midflow?
Basis hold.
Highs don't hold.
Simultaneously, extensions again filled them.
Because the core base of liquidity, the inventory of the inventory of liquidity
is most of this remaining down here.
Why is price running out?
Here's the thick by liquidity.
you have relative thin sell liquidity
When that big market order shot comes in
It's a big trade
Let's say it's 50 million
It has to go look for sell liquidity in the book
And it goes and looks for it
The sell liquidity
We know is already drawing away
So it stretches price out
The prices that that 50 million is trying to buy
The sellers
They're drawing away from price
To 50 million chasing it's stretching price out
But still down here
There might be an inventory of 50 billion
Yeah
And once that 50 million
and buy market order,
a shot dries off,
it's left behind a vacuum
and price has to draw back down
to find the inventory,
to find the liquidity
to fuel the next move.
Hence why we have this characteristic
where price runs out,
dries off,
fills the extension.
Runs out,
dries off,
fills the extension.
Even within the smaller price
runs inside of it,
price runs out,
dries off, fills the extension,
runs out,
dries off,
fills the extension,
draws back down
to the inventory
to fuel the next move.
these are the visual characteristics
as a result of the state of liquidity
and the execution methods
that are implemented when price is trading under these states
so look the context is this
extensions get filled we know that as a price behaviour
extensions get filled
bullish midflow
so we can expect it to be residual cell liquidity on the left
we don't expect it to be strong sell liquidity
all because of this
I would not expect a residual area of sell liquidity
to break the last inventory, the big shelf,
and reverse price.
So if I do take this extension fill,
I know I'm only like the possibility in my trade,
the probability of my trade is high
only up until the extension fill.
Yeah.
Do you get it?
Yeah, that makes sense.
Now, because of fractal,
here's another tool we're using.
Because of fractal, I looked at this,
I would look at this individual price swing
as a fractal, contextualize where it fits in.
This is a one minute swing
or a lower time frame,
tick chart swing inside of
which bit flow on a five minute.
So all we're seeing here
is the leg that's running out
away from the inventory.
Once that leg dries off,
we can expect it to fill.
It's a price run.
So if I'm wanting to fill that extension,
Looking at the factor price swing, it becomes super, super inefficient into that residual cell liquidity.
That's how we will manage the train, basically.
If price is going to fill, this run has to dry off.
What does it look like when everyone's drying off?
You have apex characteristics.
Yeah.
You get it.
I take my entry.
I'm looking for a shore.
What I need to see is that the inventory of buyers fails to push to new highs.
Then I want to see a barbarous shell flip and bearish midflow.
so again we're using fractal
and characteristics of price swing stages
CPS to manage the trade this time
yeah that makes sense
we used it to time the trade by waiting for that thin move
we then manage the trade using the fractal swing
the characteristics we can expect if we're right
if I'm right that the price the buyers are super weak
that up there that the core buy liquidity is down there the inventory
well the price response and the way a response throughout its duration should reflect weak bits
so CPS is basically a tool we're using to navigate the market to track probabilities manage trades
time trades and also you know it helps us align our expectations for what price should do
shouldn't do etc yeah so like what kind of what kind of stage you in
the price swing and the types of responses you can expect etc yeah so think about what we discussed
here cps is this really broad tool it basically just you know the characteristics of the swings
that we see over and over again but the use cases for it are far and wide they're massive
we discussed how we can use it to time that entry there but we uh that one there we used fractal
to contextualize where the swing fits in on the higher time frame there's still a huge imagery of
buyers in this last shelf so we wouldn't expect this residual area of sell equity to push price down
are you following me yeah yeah um so yeah you know the CPS is a full price swing
which implies that the sequence of events um you know the base the shift the continuation
the apex the breakdown they happen after one or another basically
all right so it basically is imperative to understand yeah just because price features are described
the way they are
and because
I'm saying
after the shell flip
came to midflow
etc doesn't mean
every single price
swing will
just because
this is flip
the shelf
does not mean
that this will
continue to
bearish midflow
is likely
but because of
the higher time
from I can build
a case for
why this one
I can build
a case for why
buyers should
hold this
and continue to the
upside
how these
weak sell liquidity
in this high
we've drained
it all
we grabbed it
we grabbed there, we've drained all the cell liquidity in the high,
quite easily see if I's continue.
Yeah, plus the left side's just residual, isn't it?
All this is residual.
Yeah, until just the top.
Until about that area.
But on the high time frame, this is a BA.
That's the daily BA.
Okay.
All right.
So if that's understood,
the context is considered here,
it wouldn't be a surprise if their buyers turned up here,
flip this shelf of this down move.
and went into bullish midflow
it's more likely to happen
considering what we just looked at
in the high time frame
governs and takes precedence
right so
the point here is even though I'm talking to you
I'm telling you that CPS
it goes from apex
shelf retest shifting the state of liquidity
in the bullish midflow
and then it breaks the midflow
sideways part and reverses
yeah this happens in sequences one two three four what we've had is one two
i don't think we had a clear break oh here we had a clear break actually uh yeah it wasn't
it wasn't entirely parabolic at the height yeah do you think it's just because of the timing
and then it's just on a friday no not all highs are they're going to be the same in it oh yeah
fair enough just because the more favorable price swings have a clear side base spot
this one hasn't
it's less likely to hold
that high is not a strong high
we'll discuss it a later day
but price is flip shelf
it's quite reasonable
for someone to say yeah
it has to go into bearishment flow
but we know that's not necessarily the case
because of the complexity
that higher timeframes bring in
if price was that simple
and it followed the structure every single time
we'd win every single time
you'd be a billionaire
look we have an example here
where price broke the shelf of this down move,
run higher, broke the shelf, ran lower,
broke the shelf, failed to continue on it.
Yeah.
Right?
It actually broke down.
So why are these individual price swings failing?
Up, down, up, down.
Because, broadly speaking, it wasn't a low-volume state.
On the higher time frame, that's a low-volume state, bro.
Because volume contraction, there isn't enough buying and selling to push price out.
hence why the characteristics we're seeing here is this fucking shell flip had a nice
shelf free test tried to shift into bullish midflow but it gave in it failed as a result of the
higher time frame governing context so it's a very important principle there yeah the higher time
frame takes precedence always within a low volume state there's not enough driving buying and
selling to push price out past the areas of liquidity hence why the bids here is
It wasn't bullish midfloor, but the bids here dried off quite quickly.
It actually held inside this fractal core of sell liquidity.
And that's, again, that's a B.A.
Get it? Shelf, this pushed through the shelf, that's the B.A.
Didn't this technically break?
Yeah.
We're a rich one, sorry.
Yeah, but this is the BIA that pushed it out.
It did break.
And then this pushed it.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, cool.
Oh, okay, sorry.
What you're saying
Yeah, what I'm saying is
Wouldn't the BA be somewhere like here
Because this pushed out
No, no, no.
Sorry, I should say
The BA
Pushes Price through into Midflow
Oh, okay, okay, okay, that makes me sense
Now, here, price pushed out
It didn't go into midflow
Uh-huh
Came back down
And this finally did, yeah?
Oh, okay, so then, yeah,
That would be the BA.
Okay.
In this instance,
all the bi-liquity here
was grabbed and grabbed again,
so it's straight.
Yeah.
Did you get it?
so again within this particular
example is unique in the sense
that the BA here has been drained
it's drained the liquidy
whereas the BA here has not been drained
Price them picked that out
both are BA but the context is different
there's going to be so many different variations
that are possible that you need to experience them
over time
how many variations do you think that you've seen now
in all of them
all of them
because think about the frequency of price rings here
There's one swing up, swing down, swing up, swing down.
At your stage, I was tracking every single one.
Wallahi, I'd wake up in the night and be on my phone on trailer, view,
drawing boxes.
I'm not guessing you.
I'm telling you the truth, bro.
Simply through tracking and observing, you build a deep connection with price in it.
But the tracking and observing has to be structured.
It can't be random.
You need to know what you're looking at.
Yeah.
You know, if I gave you a rocket, you know, that goes into space,
you wouldn't know what the fuck to do.
If I told you to build me a program, coding, you wouldn't know what the fuck to do unless you were introduced to the necessary framework that, you know, that coding is.
So you need to know the specific languages for coding, what each individual piece of the language means, what is used for, you break it down into a proper framework so you can apply it.
So you build a tool, you know, you build a collection of a tool toolbox.
The same thing applies to trade it.
Here you have price rings and repeat over and over.
they're exploitable because they're consistent
this edge in them
why these price swings are occurring
as a result of the market dynamics we've discussed
variable volume flow market dries off
why does price overextended
to become inefficient
is compounded
that effect is created and made worse
by the characteristics of dealers
and market makers
the liquidity provider behavior
is causing price to stretch out
is causing price to become super super thin
when nobody wants to trade up there
you get it
And that itself is greater conditions where price consistently draws back down to find liquidity over and over again.
Look, here we've seen a price run out.
The move itself traded thinly.
It wasn't significant build-up of liquidity in there.
Once that volume dried off, hit a core area of buyers there.
It took a light volume.
It wasn't strong volume here.
You can actually see it failed to really do anything for a long time.
It took a light volume to push it right.
back up to find a real area of sell equity, a thicker area of sell liquidity for a price
when it's next move. This response, this condition here is entirely different to what's going
on in the move down. Here you have a volume shot, the bids drawing away, and that volume's stretching
out. Once that volume dried off, it left a pokey of air basically there. There's a vacuum. There's a
pocket of air of liquidity. So as that volume is now dried off, it doesn't take anything. It takes
light, light buying to draw
price up. Think about it here.
There's thin sell liquidity left
and the wheel down. If anybody buys
on the dealer's ask price, the dealer does not
want to take on that short risk.
Because the probability of price going up is
really, really high.
If the dealer goes short here,
who's he going to buy up? Who's he going to sell to?
Who's he going to buy off, sorry, if there's no
sell liquidity here?
Yeah, he's taking that risk.
You've taken on a risk and basically it's exposed to a
negative position.
So what dealers do at the
points of exhaustion is to start using last look.
If someone tries to buy it at the dealer's ass price,
they'll reject it and re-quote it at a higher price.
So the cell liquidity is absolutely no cell liquidity
at the point of exhaustion.
And what remains here is a weakness as well.
When you push through the shelf,
basically on an algorithmic basis,
the cell liquidity will start to draw away.
It wants to avoid adverse selection.
after you have the
push past the shelf
here's the inventory
of sell liquidity
yeah
as price pushes through
typically it builds up
as well
what you'll get
is if there was
sell liquidity
it will draw away
to avoid getting
clipped to avoid
negative positions
okay
right so again
you have a thin
area of sell liquidity
because of the way
price was delivered
on the way down
and that itself
creates a condition
where this will happen
and if you
looked at the state
of liquidity
this is entirely
different the way price is moving up
to the way price moved down.
Yeah, much different.
Visually it is, but I'm saying you can
have like this swing year.
It looks similar. Price moved down
and then they moved up. But
the way price is moving up here,
the state of price is entirely
different to what it is when it's moving down.
Even if they look similar.
Here you have a driving force
pushing price. Here you have
low volume, lack of liquidity in the market.
Okay, I understand what you mean.
A lack of liquidity
on the sell side, actually.
So the point I'm making,
I keep making it,
these conditions are created over and over and over again
as a function of market dynamics.
So there's edge in trying to exploit these behaviours.
We know they'll occur as long as the market structure stays the same.
The general path of market structure
has stayed the same for about the last 20 years.
It basically is technological arms race.
It's electrified.
do you think you'll ever change
the only thing I can
yeah there'll be significant changes
but from what I
it depends the direction it goes
in them if they centralise everything
and all the liquidity was in one place
and the dealer stopped using last lock
this wouldn't expand as much
it'd be more efficient
so what you'd get is more price behavior like this
where price runs out draws back in
most of the price moves would be tight like that
it'd be tight rather than
massively expanding like that for example
this one here you get it
it wouldn't drive as strongly as that
it'd be much more stable and efficient
because the bi-liquidies here is 10
there would be entities that draw their bids away
on the central limit order bot
on a central exchange
but still the way prices delivered
there'd be less capacity for dealers
to control prices there
so it just depends on the direction price goes
but as of right now it's not on a central exchange
it is, but it is OTC.
The prices are mainly derived from liquidity providers,
setting prices.
So you have banks and non-banks.
They're setting their bids and offers.
And what this feed is doing,
our Dukas copy,
is taking an aggregate of the bids and offers
from multiple liquidity providers,
banks, non-banks,
and ECN venues,
and it's creating the best bid best offer them.
So here's a dealer,
here's a bank,
here's a bank, here's a bank.
Each bank has positions, yeah?
So they might be exposed to 5 million long GDP and 6 million short USD.
So they have USD exposure, yeah, 1 million short USD.
What they might want to do is reduce that exposure.
So, you know, they adjust their bids and offers based on that.
Their bid and that price might be adjusted depending on what type of risk they want to take on.
Okay.
Each of these dealers are managing their inventory risk, the inventory of liquidity they hold,
and the inventory of positions they hold.
They're also managing the risk of getting clipped by,
aggressive entities so they're all forced to control prices or to control their own prices in response
to each other. There's an information game being played. That then results in inefficiencies that
are created. So again, like this volume shot, there would have been buy liquidity there. One dealer starts
to withdraw his prices. All these other guys withdraw their prices as well. So even if there is bids in
the market, even if some client has buy liquidity there, the dealers are not with.
willing to provide their bid here because the other deals are repriced and lower.
That results in bid prices that are not accurately reflecting the true information in the market,
creates an inefficiency. The market prices that the sellers are trading on here is inefficient.
It's more expensive for them. Price is stretching further than it should.
And it creates that condition where once the volume dries off, there's a gap here inside liquidity
and light, light volume pushes it right back to find the real area.
of inventory.
Yeah, you see that so much.
It is what the FX market is.
And almost every market that exists, that is a financial market.
So gold, equities, metals, commodities, futures on SEP 500, which is basically just a fake contract.
All of these markets are similar in this sense where the entity's behavior, which is, you know, we're small fish.
This is in a perfectly competitive market.
you have entities that have much more control over it than we do.
For example, a market maker, they set the prices.
Do you get it?
If the market maker and liquidity provider competition was perfect,
by that what I mean is, you know,
if you're selling milk on a high street for 30p,
and then I sell milk for 30p as well,
and then somebody comes in and he sells for 29p,
we're all forced to sell at 29p, yeah?
and then another entity comes in that sells for 28p
then we're all forced to go to 28p
and another entity comes in that sells for 23p
trying to drive the customers to each other
eventually all these guys end up losing everything
that is a perfectly competitive market
but as we know in reality
there is no actual perfectly competitive market in the world
because we're all exploited people as humans
what will eventually happen is
two or three of these firms
will control the total supply of milk
they will make special relationships
with the producers of milk
so they only have the connection themselves
this guy cannot access milk
so cheap as these guys can
that's like
anti-competition
these guys are control of the market
they're forming an oligopoly
because of these guys' behaviours now
prices will stay about 2030p
because they're all in agreement
they all control the prices
of milk itself.
FX itself is the same.
You don't have unlimited dealers
that are competing with each other.
Sorry, you don't have unlimited
dealers. You have a collection
of 15 investment banks,
about 15, and a few non-bank
market makers that
together control the prices.
I cannot control the prices as well as
them. They have more market
power than us, basically.
As we know, if I go along,
let's say I'm a client of the bank,
and I go along
the bank has the right
to reject my trade
to not fill my trade
in my desired price
and slip it
and for some market order
the bank has the right
to you know
if they wanted to
if they didn't care
about my relationship
give me the widest spread
you can see how
they have
skewed disproportionate power
in the market
that is an example
of imperfect competition
and their behaviours
themselves
which is going to be
to protect the bottom line
to protect their profit
and increase the profit
influences the what we see in prices.
So there's this thin sell liquidity here.
An informed trader from, let's say a pension fund,
not a pension fund, from a hedge fund,
goes long with the bank.
The bank knows that this hedge fund
is unlikely to be wrong about the doubt.
Basically, they're looking at it this way.
What information does this hedge fund know
that we don't know about the future prices of GDPUSD?
They don't want to go against him.
They don't want to take the bet against it.
so they withdraw their bids
so they withdraw their offers
they pull their offers higher
making the bid chase it
stretching price out
that response from the bank
of changing their offer
is not because they are
bullish on the pound
it's because they're directly
responding to the risk of trading against this hedge
fund
that action itself
is not
it's basically not a fear action
in reality you should avoid selling the pound
if you think the pound's strong
not because you don't like trade
you don't want to take the trade against that guy
that action itself on the price go and higher
and the ask price
to avoid adverse selection
is an example of market inefficiency
if it was efficient
the price would only reflect
the information available out there
or public and private information about the pound
and private information as well
but the price that the ask price
the change in the ask price that the hedge funds trading on
is not the you know the ass price didn't change because the underlying value of pound
changed but because the dealer's behavior and the dealer has that skewed power
do you get it yeah so these actions itself the exploitive
somewhat aggressive actions of dealers which is always going to happen you will do it
i would do it we're humans it creates these conditions in marketers where
basically it becomes inefficient
price is stretching out
as a result of that inefficiency
the ask price is drawing away
the deal is avoiding risk
the bins are chasing yet stretching
stretching stretch and stretching
imagine being that buyer
your willingness to buy a higher
and higher prices is almost non-existent
you get it
so that initial volume shot
that doesn't have to be a big volume shot
causes price to stretch this forward
whilst the rest of the market
is wanting to trade down here
it is not willing
to accept that higher price.
So once that volume shot dries off,
price only stretched that far
because the dealer withdrawers offers.
Once that volume shot dries off,
left behind is hardly anything.
Do you get it?
So what we're looking at here is
the dealer behavior
cause price to stretch out.
That's it.
The effect and the result,
the consequence,
is that you get pockets of air
or gaps in liquidity,
price moves which are super, super stretched,
and there's no hardly need liquidity left behind in them.
So what it takes to push price down through that gap is little volume
over and over and over again.
So this is the real consequence.
Price having to draw back down even on very light volume to find liquidity.
It has to draw back down so far because the dealer's behaviors collectively
within the organizational structure of the market causes prices to keep stretching,
you know, consistently stretched further than they show.
that's a market and efficiency
this is the result of the market
and efficiency and happens repeatedly
consistently forever and ever and never
and that's what we're trading
we're trading that volatility
that volatility is predictable
we don't have to care about
where cable's going to be in a month's time
I don't give two shits if it's at 150
or at 120
what I do know is though
on the way to 150
it will behave in a very consistent way
on the way to 120
will behave in a very consistent way.
Do you get it?
Yeah,
they can take advantage of the behaviors
which are a function of the microstructure
completely sidesteping this need
to predict and analyze
where the price is going to be in the future,
the fundamental side.
You know what?
I'll tell you for free.
The level of information
that more advanced participants analyze,
they mine so much data,
they pay,
hundreds of grants for special data feeds
their level of analysing where price should be tomorrow
what prices should go to the true value of the pound
we can never compete with that
never ever compete with that
we're sitting at home at our fucking computers bro did you get it
we have not we do not have access to the same information
as the more advanced participants so if we collect it
you know if we consistently try to act like them
and predict where price is going to go we're much more likely to fail
you get it
they're more advanced
they have more information than us
they have a greater capacity
to move the market
they can defend
airways and prices
we can't do that
we're using a fucking
historical price chart
price moved down here
it only moved down
once the seller decided
to go shore
and then price responded
after
that's historical information
that's already happened
we're using
historical lagging information
to predict future price
movements
you see how we're only
looking at a very, very, very small piece when the sea of information that other
participants have is so much bigger. They will always be right. We will almost always lose
if we act in that way. Yeah, you can't think or I'm going to, I'm going to think like
one of them because we don't have the same level of it, but the more sophisticated, yeah?
Yeah. So I'm not saying you can't assume where, you know, you can't anticipate your
price might go, but making longer run predictions. So if I say,
price should be at $150
within the next two weeks.
I have to be right for two weeks.
What's the likelihood of
we consistently being right
for a long run period
in a market,
in a,
you know,
in an environment
that's highly complex
where the probabilities are changing
all the time,
probabilities are dynamic,
and also
we have entities
with more information than us.
And also, you have this dynamic where anything can happen at any given time.
So over the next two-week period, the UK could get invaded by Russia.
Unlikely, but it could.
If that happens, pound is not going to 150, rough.
You get it?
So making longer run predictions is much less likely to be correct
because you have to be right for a longer time.
In a condition or an environment where probably is always changing.
this information that's always coming out
there's an infinite amount of
variables that can combine
to cause a different
you know to cause an event
infinite
Boris Johnson's mom could die so he presses a nuclear burn
fucking Theresa May could be a devil
you get it like aliens could invade us
there's an infinite amount
of variables that could
combine and cause an event that we don't know
so there's known unknowns
and there's unknown unknowns
and probably is always changed
and there's more advanced participants than us
and we're trying to make predictions where price is going to be
are you fucking crazy though
it's absolutely ridiculous
and then you have the low level retail
which use historical price charts to predict future movements
that's like looking at a fucking coin flip chart
and seeing trends on it
you know here's a coin flip chart we flipped it a thousand times
heads tails so here you had a sequence of tails
here you had a sequence of heads etc etc
just because this has happened
does not mean
it will consistently happen
you get it
there's no edge there's 50 50 probability
so sometimes you'll get it
sometimes you won't get it
there's no positive expectancy
over the longer one you will not make money that way
there's actual people
in this fucking dunya bro
trading prices thinking have a positive
expectancy just because it happened before
price could
you know any number of things could happen
basically
infinite amount is
so I keep tying it back to this point
it helps shape your view of the market
we need edge
this is where the edges
in the behaviours created as a result
of the market structure
and basically the macro structure
the behaviours of trade etc
think about it
price run out they dry it off and it's now drawn back in
that is repeating
on a one minute chart
all the way to a weekly chart
you get it
price traded thinly on the way down
dried off left behind that void
any buying that comes through
light light buying is able to push price
right through that thinness
back to the thicker area of liquidity
do you get it
so
that's the behavior we're focusing on
that's the microch
that's the volatility
that we want to be exploiting
but obviously on the one minute short
it's like a four-pit move
we don't care about it
whereas this bigger one or that bigger one is much more favourable and they're exactly the same
this is the same as that you have apex fractal apex shot and price draws right back to the core
time and time again just like here you have a fractal apex price runs out and they draw away right back to
the core you have a fractal apex price runs out on the drawers where right back to the core through the thin parts
through the thick parts.
That's the structure
of which price moves.
So we break it down.
It's called characteristic of price rates.
It's a tool we use to navigate price,
contextualize price.
We know why we need to contextualize it
so we can accurately identify the best way
to trade it,
to engage it.
We use it to time trades.
So if I'm looking to short this extension
and fill this extension,
do I just short it really nearly with my eyes close
at every single level?
Or do I wait for this fractal swing
to show weakness and exhaustion
and time it?
let me just annotate it yeah
so yeah
the mid flow down
then you got the shelf
shelf flip
yeah
then shelf retest
then back into
midflow
then
well it's not even
it was meant to be like a
pop parabolic
well parabolic phase
and then
in the successful
in the good swing yeah
you know there's variations in swings
yeah not all the swing
like
Right now, we don't know this has been a hold of breakdown.
Probabilistically, because of the weight is high formed and price didn't have that parabolic phase,
I wouldn't expect it to hold.
To get it, within this particular variation.
But when we look at, like this one, for example,
Price had a significant surge,
became super-super-parabolic,
and I would expect that high to hold, which it did.
You're fully filled it back down to the core.
You get it?
Yeah.
And we even responded back of the core.
but in other case
successful swings
they become parabolic at the high
not all of the swings will
the air price run
it becomes parabolic at the high
it doesn't matter what time frame
you look at it on becomes parabolic at the high
and the lowest
just because the more favourable ones do
doesn't mean that all of them will be favourable
the same way that just because price has
has shipped the show doesn't mean it will go into
bullish milk yeah yeah it is likely to
that don't mean that it's going to
definitely happen
definitively yeah so
So that's why we need to break price swing stages down
and set relative probabilistic expectations
what price is going to do.
We use it to track probabilities.
So here you have a price swing.
We know likely because the bearish midflow
hasn't broken, it should continue.
Then price breaks the midflow.
I then know I'm looking for a sideways pop.
Once I get the pop, I am then looking
for the shelf to fail or even break
and not be able to push any lows.
Once price gets to the shelf,
I'm expecting to win the bullish midflow,
but we haven't.
We've drawn all the way back down
to buy liquidity.
We've grabbed all the bioliquity.
Technically, it's not invalid here.
It could still shift out.
It is a show.
Yeah.
It tries to shift out and it finally fires.
Because, you know, comparing,
if you compared what happened in this swing,
the characteristics of this one,
the successful swing,
you'll see very, very stark,
they'll lose significant differences
in what a price was.
If you follow it,
step, my step.
Yeah.
There's a significant difference.
Over time, you'll be able to identify the characteristics of losers as they happen
and differentiate between the characteristics of winning apexes as they happen, and successful
price swings as they happen.
But you can only do that if you've experienced that losers.
And if you've experienced how swings fail and apex is fair.
So that's why when you're tracking, you don't know what the price is going to do, his price,
you don't know what it's going to do next.
But what you do know is that you can contextualize it.
we do know that price swings have price swing stages
each of them have individual unique characteristics
we can identify those characteristics to identify the stage
we know what happens after each stage is a sequence
in the successful swings
so when you're tracking price
you'll be certain expectations that prices flip shelf
so it should go into bullish midflow and it all fails in that
and then you have an experience of what failed price
wins look like yeah get it
you know what price should do shouldn't be
you use it to track probabilities
of what price is going to do next
if I'm long here
and prices now starting to absorb
all the buy inventory in this apex
and this pickup
I know now
it has to move to the upside
so if price is drained
all the available by liquidity
is grab this level
it's ground the bottom
it's drained the inventory
if now price starts to fail here
the probability of it
going to my stop is almost
100%.
You get it
so before
reaches my stock and you can only do this though once you've experienced the characteristics
of winnings and users over and over and over again and you can use the tool just because
i'm introducing with the cps doesn't mean you can use it yet yeah you have to train and you know
learn to use it but in the case it's used to track probably select trades
time your trades i'm looking for a reversal price and bearish there's no fucking time you know i'm
I'm timing there's no trade deal I wait for that break and I want the park
simultaneously I'm using CPS to select my levels I'm using fractal on the left
there might be a core area by the goodie you get it yeah so I've used CPS to select
my level I'm using CPS the time on trade now to manage it I take my entry what I
want to see in this practical price ring is at least price response draw back up
to show so polish fractal shell fit polish midflow on the lower high frame I want to see
price fell to push the new lows
and I don't want to, et cetera, et cetera.
In other case,
price could play like any given second
because probably it's a dynamic
and not all price swings will be successful.
You have to understand that
the price swing that we're looking at
is of a successful price swing.
Not all price swings will be successful
so we have to,
we don't set definitive expectations
of our price doing certain things.
So in other words,
just because price is flip a shop
doesn't mean you can buy it
and you'll break out.
If you do that, you're playing a randomness then.
You're trading like, you know, is their edge in buying after every shelved?
No, not alone.
I can show you many, many shelflets that fret.
For example, you would have had a shelter there when price broke down.
That didn't shift down.
If you sold it there, you fucked up.
You would have had many, many, many bearer shellfish in the lower time thing.
That they all fucked up many, many times.
So, in isolation, just waiting for price swing to break shelf and then buying it has no edge alone.
What we can do is, though, introduce context, introduce all the variables that increases the likelihood of the shell flip turning into a midflow.
Things like picking up a core area, things like the price swing having loads of weakness in it and haven't actually broke midflow the sideways spot.
Then when price breaks that shell, if you short it then, you short it then.
you can show it there's a higher probability that price will go your way so you can introduce
variables which includes the likelihood of shell clip going away but in isolation just the price the
shell clip alone is not likely to consistently shift in the flow so that's why if we don't use
CPS to set rigid strict expectations for a price you do rather guide our expectations based
of experience based on context what price is likely to do what it should be what it will look like in
situation. We use fractal to track it. Each individual outcome is using a fractal
swimming to track it. I'll give an example. Here's a base of liability. Prices run into it.
I need to assess this move in isolation to see if the buyers are responded or not, if it is
salivacism there. Imagine this is a H1 shot. If I want to time the longing in this move,
I can't just buy it with ice cream. I have to wait for it to show that parabolic exhaustion
that weakness of the lows
you follow me
so we use fractal to track price
and time trades
and select trades etc
select our levels
it's critical that you can understand
yeah why I'm just talking about this
so consistently so the task
I'm going to set you is quite a basic one
I want to find two guys swings
where you've annotated them fully
including
basically
basically you're annotated
I want you to find the
are we want you to find the shows.
Okay.
In every single price win, there's two runs in it.
You have the run up and you have the run down.
So this will have a show, this will have a show.
There'll be two apes.
There'll be two BAs.
What you might have on the lower time frame as well is fractal apex in here.
If I blow this off as zoom into it, prices and abolished midflow,
it drew down and it builds up of glass industry, a fractal apex shell fit.
You get it.
Yeah, yeah.
That might be a fractal apex as well inside the bullish midflow.
I want you to differentiate between them.
These are the cores.
These are the factors.
Okay.
What also want you to do is, in this price swing, you might draw, like, further away, arrows.
I want you to simply call this apex, break of shelf.
What that means, what each of these mean, by the way, as well.
Okay.
What's going on in the apex?
You know, we're seeing the apex formation itself is of seeing the shape.
Shelf failed to push any of those indicative of what?
Weakness on the cell.
Yeah.
Price breaking shelf increases the likelihood of sellers drawing away.
It confirms the weakness and then the BA if you see low volume states,
when you can describe it.
But basically, you need to also identify the price of the stages.
So Apex, shelf flip, shift in the state of liquidity, what does that mean?
Shift the state to liquidity, midflow, and then the reverses.
So you keep trying to do this, connect the concept with what we're seeing on the prices, yeah?
So you have two sides.
You have your understanding of what prices, and then you have the actual price room, yeah?
The actual price and features, the visual stuff.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's fine.
To internalize it, yeah?
So on the left-hand side, the conceptual understanding is like why price moves,
why price behaves the way it is.
As we discussed today, I think it became a bit clearer for you today.
I don't know, but why do we consistently seeing these price behaviors occur?
over and over again, right?
Y'all can hear you.
Yeah, yeah, I can hear you, yeah.
So we discussed why these behaviours keep a curve.
That's your understanding of why price moves,
equity dynamics, principles, deal in the behavior,
the effects of it, the more constructive, etc.
And then on the right-hand side of the visuals,
what you're seeing in charts,
where you need your skill to implement it,
where you need to break it down like a language
so you can isolate
and it categorize
things separately
because each thing
is individual
in this nature
is like
a core area
of liquidity
is entirely different
to a residual area of equity
the two separate things
all of the both equity
basis
this has much more
significance than the residual
yeah
all right
so
within this practically
price rate
not not the big one
So, I should do it this way, right?
So this area of core liquidity has much more significance than that,
even at the both liquidity basis.
So what we need is, like, you need to be able to differentiate.
If we just call both of these liquidity bases,
it would imply that they're both the same.
Yeah, they're not the same, yeah.
You need to separate them, right?
Just the same way you need to push here and not.
Separate your legs from your arms.
They both have muscles in the end.
They both have different functions, though.
The same thing applies with trading.
We need to have the necessary language at least
to accurately
to accurately contextualize
and categorize
things appropriately for what they are
and differentiate in between them.
So a shelf is different to a core.
A BA is inside the core,
which is likely a good level.
A residual area is shit.
Some areas, like sometimes a BA,
a shelter meter, sorry, can be washed.
Sometimes there won't be.
If we never identified what wash levels are,
you know, it limits our ability to successfully pick good levels and bad levels, basically.
Yeah.
But that's the point.
Imagine you like a table, on the left-hand side, you have the conception of understanding,
on the right-hand side you have your visual understanding, you know, the visual framework.
Understanding mechanics of price movement,
how liquidity is directly related to the volatility,
it results in a deeper condition
of what you're seeing in charts.
If you look at charts in the right way
in the appropriate way for what it is,
you don't know what's going to happen next,
we need to put a question a certain way,
we need edge,
you are looking at the problem of trading
and trying to make money,
trying to predict the future
more appropriately than your competitors.
So in the learning phase, it is complex,
but the actual implementation of strategy is more simple.
Yeah, the difference between the two
were, yeah, you've made very clear.
right so all of this will result in when you're pulling the trigger and taking the trade you can do it without hesitation knowing that what you're taking advantage of is consistent and true why it's true it results in a deeper confidence in what you're doing at charles right it so it's important basically the point in making it's important to connect the price the visual price all its stages all the individual nuances
imagine like how subtle a break of midflow is and what that means
nobody ever looks at that
they consider it noise we're actually looking at that information
and we're extracting extracting a lot of
you know it gives us edge overduces that don't know about
it allows us to see weakness in moves that other people
will wait for the break of structure
it helps us anticipate and see things before us
so a very very small
such detail like a break of its fucking base
you get it
where it's important
that you connect
everything that we're discussing
with the concept
and then eventually the goal
is to find a combination of characteristics
as you're exercising
and your understanding of those
a combination of characteristics
like price features
that together lead to consistent traits
that's why we're separating
the entire environments
you have different types of trades here
but in either case
what are the combination of features
that you want for a price response?
well we want an area of liquidity and a weak move into it that will cause a price response so we're able to identify under which environment specifically and which parameters specifically we require to increase the probability of the initial response of our trade yeah that is only that that can only happen if you understand what's going on behind the scenes behind the price itself prices the last the last thing that occurs this price is historically
this move is now historical
it already happened
the information that the seller had
is already at a price
we have now missed it basically
we have missed that move it's all historical
so in order to like
successfully connect
your understanding
with the visual
you have to be aware of it and do it deliberately
you have to go through that difficult phase
like right now
of trying to connect these two together
you have to sit there in your own time
you have to sit there and think that shit through
even though it will be adverse in it
even though it will be difficult
you have to write things down
and have to extract as much information as you can
so the whole point is building the deeper conviction
that's the reason we're connecting it
you will not do this successfully
if you build your ability
to you know in prices
but you haven't built your ability
with your conception
understanding they have to build together okay so if your ability to see your prices follows up your
conception understanding has to draw you know develop with it in conjunction with it connect the prices
with the concept that's the point so anyway that's why we're looking at these prices